Okay, today's daf is קז, Kof-Zayin, the end is in sight, קז
Kof-Zayin 107 in מנחות. Menachot. We pick up at the משנה Mishna
about a third of the way down on קז Kof-Zayin עמוד א'.
Amud Aleph. הרי
עלי יין, Harei Alai Yayin, so our משניות Mishnayot are dealing with
different people that take different vows of bringing
different things starting with מנחות, Menachot, but then different things that are
inanimate objects to be put on the מזבח, Mizbeach, and what is
A, the first חידוש Chiddush that you're able to do that, but
then the focus of the משנה Mishna is what is the minimum
amount. Somebody says, I obligate myself to bring wine, and we've learned
before that you can bring wine by itself the same way that
it is brought by the מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim by the flour
and oil and wine that accompanies sacrifices. So somebody accepts upon himself
to bring wine, לא יפחות משלושה לוגים, Lo Yifchot Mi-Shlosha Lugim, it
can't be less than three לוג Log because that is a minimum
amount that is brought for the נסכים. Nesachim. רביעית ההין לכבש יין,
Revi’it Ha-Hin Lakaves Yayin, a quarter of a הין. Hin. A הין
Hin is 12 לוג, Log, so that is three לוג. Log. שמן,
Shemen, if somebody obligates themselves to bring oil, and that was a
debate before in the משנה, Mishna, and this is assuming you can
obligate yourself to bring oil by itself, right? Wine by itself exists,
it gets with the מנחת נסכים, Minchat Nesachim, but it's you know,
the wine, even though it comes with the flour and oil, the
wine stands separate. The oil normally comes to get mixed together with
the flour, but nevertheless according to this position, you can go ahead
and bring like רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, you can go ahead and
bring oil by itself. So if somebody says oil, how much? לא
יפחות מלוג, Lo Yifchot Mi-Log, no less than a לוג Log because
a לוג Log is the amount of oil that would come with
a standard
מנחה. Mincha. רבי אומר שלושה לוגים, Rabbi Omer Shlosha Lugim, רבי Rabbi
says three לוג Log because since the basis of this presumably is
the מנחת נסכים, Minchat Nesachim, so there the minimum amount of oil
would be three לוג. Log. You don't look at a normal מנחה,
Mincha, you look at a מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim. פירשתי ואיני יודע
מה פירשתי, Perashti Ve-Eini Yodea Ma Perashti, if I said how much
לוג Log but I don't remember how much of oil, יביא כיום
מרובה, Yavi Ke-Yom Merube, you bring like the day of the largest
day, okay, like a day of plenty. So we'll see what that
means. You might have a good guess based on an earlier discussion
in the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, אזרח, Ezrach, right? So
it says the פסוק Pasuk is אזרח Ezrach by the נסכים, Nesachim,
כל האזרח יעשה ככה, Kol Ha-Ezrach Yaaseh Kacha, every citizen shall do
this. An extra פסוק, Pasuk, it's a little funny after it said
to bring the נסכים. Nesachim. So to tell you, מלמד שמתנדבין יין,
Melamed She-Mitnadvim Yayin, that you could bring wine, that somehow that extra
פסוק Pasuk tells you that you can do this even separate from
a קרבן. Korban. וכמה, Ve-Kama, and how much? שלושה לוגים, Shlosha Lugim,
three לוג Log because that is the minimum. ומנין שאם רצה להוסיף
יוסיף, U-Minyan She-Im Ratza Le-Hosif Yosif, how do you know that you
can do more than three לוג? Log? תלמוד לומר Talmud Lomar יהיה,
Yihye, יהיה Yihye because it says ככם כגר כאזרח יהיה, Ke-Chachem Ka-Ger
Ka-Ezrach Yihye, okay, so there's like even more that you can do.
יכול יפחות, Yachol Yifchot, maybe you can do less than three לוג?
Log? תלמוד לומר ככה, Talmud Lomar Kacha, it has to be exactly.
So it has to be minimum, you know, of what the minimum
is, three לוג, Log, but it can be any more. All right,
and we'll see a little more about that going on. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
שמן לא יפחות מלוג רבי אומר שלושה לוגים, Shemen Lo Yifchot Mi-Log
Rabbi Omer Shlosha Lugim, so one לוג Log and רבי Rabbi says
three לוג. Log. במאי קמיפלגי, Be-Mai Ka-Miflegi, what is their debate about?
אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב פפא, Amru Rabbanan Kamei De-Rav Pappa, so the
Rabbis said this discussion in front of רב פפא, Rav Pappa, בדון
מינה ומינה ובדון מינה ואוקי באתרה קמיפלגי. Be-Don Minah U-Minah U-Ve-Don Minah
Ve-Oki Be-Atrah Ka-Miflegi. The question is, when you learn A from B,
do you take let's say B is teaching you something about, well
let's say A is teaching you something about B, do you take
what is the case of A, apply it to B, and then
bring with it the original context of A? That's דון מינה ומינה,
Don Minah U-Minah, or do you apply it to B, but then
apply to it the context of B? דון מינה ואוקי באתרה, Don
Minah Ve-Oki Be-Atrah, learn from it but put it in the place
of its destination. For those familiar with cut and paste in the
computer language, is it, are you pasting with the source destination or
with the,
what is it, with the source formatting or with the destination formatting?
So דון מינה ומינה Don Minah U-Minah is the source formatting and
דון מינה ואוקי באתרה Don Minah Ve-Oki Be-Atrah is the destination formatting.
Okay, so let's take a look how this works.
רבנן סברי, Rabbanan Savri, the Rabbis held
דון מינה ומינה, Don Minah U-Minah, you learn from it and you
take it with the source formatting. מה מנחה משתנדבין אף שמן נמי
משתנדבין? Ma Mincha Mishtandvin Af Shemen Nami Mishtandvin? ומינה מה מנחה בלוג
אף שמן בלוג. U-Minah Ma Mincha Be-Log Af Shemen Be-Log. Okay, so
as opposed to wine which is learned from the מנחת נסכים Minchat
Nesachim which we learned just above, כל האזרח יעשה ככה, Kol Ha-Ezrach
Yaaseh Kacha, the idea that you could bring oil by itself according
to this is learned from the standard מנחה, Mincha, because it says
by the standard מנחה, Mincha, אדם
כי יקריב מכם קרבן לה', Adam Ki Yakriv Mikem Korban Lashem, ונפש
כי תקריב קרבן מנחה לה'. Ve-Nefesh Ki Takriv Korban Mincha Lashem. So
the word
קרבן... Korban... so the actual basis, the פסוק pasuk we're basing the
idea of oil by itself is by a מנחה. mincha. And by
a normal מנחה mincha there's one לוג log of oil. So let's
take a look. רבנן סברי דמינו מינו, Rabbanan savri dominu mino, מה
מנחה מתנדבין, ma mincha misnadvin, the same way the קרבן korban is
learned from מנחה, mincha, the same way you can dedicate a מנחה,
mincha, you can give a מנחה mincha to be burnt on the
מזבח, mizbeach, אף שמן נמי מתנדבין, af shemen nami misnadvin, oil as
well. ומינה, umina, but take it from the original context of מנחה.
mincha. מה מנחה בלוג, ma mincha belog, the same way מנחה mincha
has a לוג log of oil, אף שמן בלוג, af shemen belog,
so oil also by itself is a לוג. log. ורבי סבר veRabbi
savar and Rabbi is of the opinion דמינו ואוקי באתרא, dominu ve'oki
be'atra, learn from it but apply it, the context of the place
that you are applying it to. מה מנחה מתנדבין אף שמן נמי
מתנדבין, ma mincha misnadvin af shemen nami misnadvin, fine, the source is
מנחה, mincha, so from מנחה mincha קרבן מנחה korban mincha you learn
that the same way you can give a מנחה mincha you can
give oil by itself, ואוקי באתרא ve'oki be'atra but put it in
its destination place. כנסכים, kenesachim, like the נסכים nesachim because in the
end where do we see the model of bringing oil, you know,
not mixed in a מנחה, mincha, I mean not exactly, but we
see the model of bringing oil, you know, similar to wine by
the נסכים nesachim you bring wine by itself, so the נסכים nesachim
is somehow seen as the model or the application, the anchor of
where we see the idea that you can bring things that are
not a מנחה mincha and liquids by themselves and it could be
true by wine it could be true by oil, okay, so you're
by the word קרבן korban from מנחה mincha you're learning the idea
but ultimately you're anchoring it in the reality of the מנחת נסכים.
minchat nesachim. So if you're anchoring it in the reality of the
מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim,
מה נסכים שלושה לוגין, ma nesachim shelosha login, so the same way
נסכים nesachim the minimum amount of oil is three לוג, log, אף
שמן נמי שלושה לוגין, af shemen nami shelosha login, so oil also
three לוג. log. Okay, so that's assuming that we, it's clear that
you learn the word from קרבן korban from מנחה, mincha, but that
the phenomenon that you're anchoring it in is in the מנחת נסכים.
minchat nesachim. Okay, אמרו ליה רבנן דבי רב פפא, amru lei rabanan
debei Rav Pappa, so that was what the rabbinic students said in
front of רב פפא. Rav Pappa. רב פפא Rav Pappa said back
to them, אי ממנחה גמר לה לרבי דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דמינו
מינו, ei mimincha gamar lah leRabbi dechulei alma lo pligi dominu mino,
if we really agree that you're learning it from מנחה, mincha, so
everybody would agree מנחה mincha is the basis, apply the original basis
and it's one לוג. log. אלא רבי מאזרח גמר לה, ela Rabbi
me'ezrach gamar lah, this makes a little more sense, right? Because ultimately
both in the case of a standard מנחה mincha and מנחת נסכים
minchat nesachim the oil is mixed with the flour. So why to
understand that you're learning from one and applying to the other is
less clear. So he says the real debate is which one are
you learning from? The רבנן Rabbanan learn from a standard מנחה, mincha,
it's one לוג. log. רבי Rabbi learns straight from מנחת נסכים, minchat
nesachim, that's three לוג. log.
Okay, רבי מאזרח גמר לה. Rabbi me'ezrach gamar lah. כל האזרח יעשה
ככה, kol ha'ezrach ya'aseh kachah, אזרח ezrach is coming to teach you
not just the idea you can bring wine by itself but you
can bring oil by itself. That's a much more elegant learning. Okay,
אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב נתן לרב פפא, amar lei Rav
Huna berei deRav Natan leRav Pappa, Rav Huna said to Rav Pappa,
ומי מצית אמרת הכי, umi mazit amrat hachi, how could you say
that? והתניא vehatanya and we taught in a ברייתא, braita, קרבן korban
basing itself on the word קרבן korban by a standard מנחה, mincha,
מלמד שמתנדבין שמן, melamed shemitnadvin shemen, it's oil, that teaches you שמן,
shemen, וכמה vekama and how much, שלושה לוגין, shelosha login, three לוג,
log, so מאן שמעת ליה דאמר שלושה לוגין רבי, man shamat lei
de'amar shelosha login Rabbi, so this idea of three לוג log that's
Rabbi's position, וקגמיר לה מקרבן vekagmir lah mikorban and in the ברייתא
braita the opinion of three לוג log is learned from the word
קרבן korban by a normal מנחה. mincha. So you see that even
though you're learning it from a מנחה, mincha, somehow you're applying it
to מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim and that's how Rabbi is getting three
לוג, log, not by learning it straight from מנחת נסכים. minchat nesachim.
אמר ליה amar lei and he said back to him, אי תניא
תניא, ei tanya tanya, look, if it's a ברייתא braita it's a
ברייתא, braita, then okay, I can't argue on that, you know, conceptually
I would say it makes sense to think Rabbi learns it all
from מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, but if you're right, if it's a
ברייתא braita and it starts with מנחה mincha and ends with מנחת
נסכים, minchat nesachim, so be it. Okay, פירשתי ואיני יודע מה פירשתי,
pirashti ve'eini yode'a mah pirashti,
if you don't know how much oil you said, יביא כיום מרובה,
yavi keyom merubeh, you bring like the day of plenty, so וכמה
vekama and how much is that? תנא כיום טוב הראשון של חג
שחל להיות בשבת, tana keyom tov harishon shel chag shechal lihyot beShabbat,
we had that before, first day of, you know, of, of סוכות
Sukkot that's on שבת, Shabbat, that's when you bring the maximum number
because maximum number of קרבנות, korbanot, so maximum number of מנחת נסכים
minchat nesachim then of, you know, that go with all the קרבנות
korbanot and that is how much we assume you mean by the
maximum. Okay, next משנה. mishnah. הרי
עלי עולה, harei alai olah, we quoted this the other day.
Somebody says I obligate myself in an עולה, olah, יביא כבש, yavi
keves, you bring a lamb. That's considered the smallest of the עולות.
olot. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר או תור או בן יונה, Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah omer o tor o ben yonah, either a turtledove
or a young pigeon,
which is even presumably even smaller, it's birds. So all of those
are עולות, olot, all of those are in the opening, you know,
פרשה, parsha, פרק
פסוקים perek pesukim of ויקרא. Vayikra. It would seem that the debate
is that most people normally think a קרבן korban is mammal, right?
Birds are sometimes, you know, in the תורה Torah if you can't
afford a higher one, sometimes the תורה Torah allows a bird, but
certainly cows, sheeps and goat are considered the standard. So maybe the
first opinion is the smallest of the standard and then רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria says, no, it's just the objectively
smallest. But we'll see how the גמרא Gemara explains the debate.
פירשתי מן הבקר ואיני יודע מה פירשתי. Peirashiti min habakar v’eini yodeia
mah peirashiti. I said it from the cattle, but I don't remember
what I said. Did I say a cow? Did I say a
calf? So יביא פר ועגל. yavi par v’egel. So bring both like
a, you know, an ox and a calf. Okay, not a cow,
that's female. עולה Olah is male. Okay. מן הבהמה ואיני יודע מה
פירשתי. Min habehemah v’eini yodeia mah peirashiti. I said I would bring
from the בהמה, behemah, like the mammals, but I don't remember which
what specific animal I said. So you have to bring all types.
יביא פר ועגל איל שעיר גדי וטלה, Yavi par v’egel, ayil, sa’ir,
gedi u’taleh, you know, an ox and a calf, a ram which
is a more adult sheep, and a goat, a גדי gedi which
is a kid goat and a טלה taleh which is a ewe,
a baby sheep. Okay, no, ewe is female. Whatever it is, a
lamb.
Okay, so that's assuming that when you are explicating what you're bringing,
you're not just saying like, you know, this like like from sheep,
you know, but you're saying... it's assuming you would have distinguished between
a ram and a, you know, and a lamb, between an adult
goat and a kid goat. All right, so because you don't know
which you said, but you said one of those, you have to
bring all of them.
פירשתי ואיני יודע מה פירשתי. Peirashiti v’eini yodeia mah peirashiti. Now, if
you say I explained but I don't know what I explained, but
now the only difference here is you didn't say it was a
בהמה, behemah, you said some type of an עולה olah but I
don't remember which one.
So מוסיף עליהם תור ובן יונה. mosif aleihem tor u’ven yonah. So
that now also includes the possibility of a turtle dove and a
pigeon, so you also have to bring those. That also might be
what you said. הרי עלי תודה ושלמים. Harei alai todah u’shlamim. If
somebody says I will... I obligate myself in a תודה todah and
the vav here means or a שלמים, shlamim, then what is the
minimum? יביא כבש. Yavi keves. So that is not
a bird, that has to be a... so therefore the minimum is...
is a lamb.
פירשתי מן הבקר ואיני יודע מה פירשתי. Peirashiti min habakar v’eini yodeia
mah peirashiti. I said that it would be type of cattle, but
I don't remember which specific type. And because it's a שלמים shlamim
or a תודה, todah, you can... it can be male or female.
So you have to
bring, so יביא פר ופרה עגל ועגלה, yavi par u’parah egel v’eglah,
an ox, a cow, a male calf and a female calf, because
it could have been any of those. מן הבהמה ואיני יודע מה
פירשתי. Min habehemah v’eini yodeia mah peirashiti. Of the animals, you know,
of mammals, but I don't remember which specific one. So now you
have to bring all of the types but male and female. פר
ופרה עגל ועגלה איל ורחל, Par u’parah egel v’eglah, ayil v’racheil, so
a ram and... so in addition to all the types of cows,
a ram and an adult female sheep, I don't know what word
there is for that in English. שעיר ושעירה, Sa’ir u’se’irah, a male
and a female adult goat, גדי וגדיה, gedi u’gediyah, a male and
female kid goat, טלה וטליה, taleh u’tlayah, and a ewe and a
lamb, or a lamb and a ewe. הרי עלי שור, Harei alai
shor, יביא הוא ונסכיו במנה. yavi hu v’nesachav b’maneh. If some... now
somebody says I obligate myself in an ox, okay, for an עולה,
olah,
or maybe a שלמים. shlamim. Anyway, what is the minimum amount you
have to spend? So the minimum amount is a מנה. maneh. All
right. עגל, Egel, יביא הוא ונסכיו בחמש. yavi hu v’nesachav b’chamesh. If
you say a calf, then it is it plus the נסכים, nesachim,
the total cost of everything is five. Five what? So that's five
סלע sela which is 20 דינר. dinar. So a מנה maneh is
100 דינר, dinar, five סלע sela is 20 דינר. dinar. Okay, so
that is a fifth of what you would bring for... for the
ox is what you're going to bring for the calf. איל, Ayil,
if you say a ram, יביא הוא ונסכיו בשתים. yavi hu v’nesachav
b’shtayim. Then that is... that is two סלע, sela, okay? So that
is... that is 10...
excuse me, eight דינר. dinar. כבש, Keves, יביא הוא ונסכיו בסלע. yavi
hu v’nesachav b’sela. So and if you say a כבש, keves, then
it is one סלע, sela, which is four דינר. dinar. So that
gives you a good idea of the relative cost of these things,
right? A lamb is... is four דינר dinar and an ox is
100 דינר, dinar, 25 times the cost of a lamb. Now רש"י
Rashi says we sort of know this stuff from like הלכה למשה
מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai says תורה שבעל פה, Torah she'be'al peh, right?
But it could just be that this is תוספות Tosafos sort of
questions that, it could just be that this was like the standard,
what we assume you meant, the normal, the average cost of these
things and so on. שור במנה, Shor b’maneh, יביא במנה חוץ מנסכיו.
yavi b’maneh chutz m’nesachav. If you explicitly say an ox with a
מנה, maneh, 100 דינר, dinar, then because you explicitly said an ox
with a מנה, maneh, then that 100 דינר dinar you spend on
the ox and not including the cost of the נסכים, nesachim, of
the wine and flour and oil.
עגל בחמש יביא בחמש חוץ מן הנסכים. Egel be-chamesh yavi be-chamesh chutz
min hanesachim. Similarly if you said a calf with five סלע, sela,
twenty דינר, dinar, then it is that is the cost you're spending
on the calf, not including the cost of the נסכים nesachim when
you don't explicate and that amount is implicit, it's for the whole
bundle. כבש בסלע יביא בסלע חוץ מן הנסכים. Keves be-sela yavi be-sela
chutz min hanesachim. It's the same in terms of the lamb. שור
במנה והביא שניים במנה לא יצא. Shor be-maneh vehevi shnayim be-maneh lo
yatza. If you say I obligate myself in an ox for let's
say an עולה olah with a מנה, maneh, a hundred דינר, dinar,
and you bring two oxen that their total cost is a hundred
דינר, dinar, you didn't fulfill your obligation because you said an ox
costing a hundred מנה. maneh. That makes sense. ואפילו זה במנה חסר
דינר וזה במנה חסר דינר. Ve'afilu zeh be-maneh chaser dinar ve-zeh be-maneh
chaser dinar. Even if one cost ninety-nine מנה maneh and one cost
ninety-nine מנה, maneh, so you spent almost double what you said you
were going to spend, you did not fulfill your obligation because you
said an ox of a hundred מנה maneh and you did not
bring an ox that was worth a hundred מנה. maneh. שחור והביא
לבן, לבן והביא שחור. Shachor vehevi lavan, lavan vehevi shachor. If you
said I'm going to bring a black one, you bring a white
one, white one you bring a black one. גדול והביא קטן לא
יצא. Gadol vehevi katan lo yatza. A big one you bring a
small one, you don't fulfill your obligation. And now the חידוש chiddush
and we said this the other day, קטן והביא גדול יצא. Katan
vehevi gadol yatza. If you said I'm going to bring a small
one and you bring a big one, you fulfill your obligation. רבי
אומר לא יצא. Rebbi omer lo yatza. Rebbi says you do not.
And Rebbi's position here actually makes sense because a large ox is
not a small ox with something more. It's a completely different type
of an ox. But presumably the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma feels that
when you say small, you mean minimum small. I'm not obligating myself
in anything more than a small, but you don't mean exactly a
small. Okay, it makes more sense in our earlier case when you
said I'm going to bring X amount of עשרונות isronot of flour
and you bring more. There at least your more contains your less.
All right, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. ולא פליגי
מר כי אתריה ומר כי אתריה. Velo pligi, mar ki atreih umar
ki atreih. So going back to the debate when you say an
עולה, olah, do you mean a lamb or do you mean a
bird, a turtledove or you know a pigeon? So it says they're
not really debating. In one place lambs were the least expensive, in
one place the turtledoves were the least expensive. I really don't know
any place where a lamb would be less expensive than a turtledove.
I would think they do debate whether you know we assume you
mean the normal context is mammals, so do we assume when you
go to the minimum, you go within the normal context or you
look at the absolute minimum. Not how the גמרא Gemara explains it.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Rabbis taught: הרי עלי עולה בסלע למזבח יביא
כבש שאין לך דבר שקרב בסלע לגבי מזבח אלא כבש. Harei alai
olah be-sela lamizbe'ach yavi keves she'ein lecha davar shekarev be-sela legabei mizbe'ach
ela keves. If somebody says I obligate myself to bring something on
the מזבח mizbe'ach for a סלע, sela, so again when you just
say something on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, we had a discussion before you
know do you mean קטורת, ketoret, the frankincense and so on. But
here when you say a סלע, sela, we assume that that means
a lamb because there is nothing that
is offered on the מזבח mizbe'ach that costs a סלע sela except
for lamb שקרב בסלע shekarev be-sela that is offered that costs a
סלע. sela. Right, as we saw in the משנה, Mishnah, that is
the standard cost of a lamb. פירשתי ואיני יודע מה פירשתי יביא
מכל דבר שקרב בסלע לגבי מזבח. Perashti ve'eini yode'a mah perashti yavi
mikol davar shekarev be-sela legabei mizbe'ach. I said it but I can't
remember what I said. Then you bring any possible thing that the
entire thing would cost a סלע. sela. So you know maybe you
can get I don't know a cheap ram, maybe you can get
like a לבונה levonah or something of that nature. Now but it
has to be a whole thing cause you said I will bring
an item for a סלע, sela, so you have to consider all
of the items that might cost a סלע. sela. But without explicating
we assume the standard thing you mean is the standard thing that
goes for a סלע sela which is the lamb. Okay,
so let's see. פירשתי מן הבקר ואיני יודע מה פירשתי יביא פר
ועגל. Perashti min habakar ve'eini yode'a mah perashti yavi par ve'egel. If
you said a cattle but you didn't say which, it has to
be a calf
and an ox. So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי? Amai? Why? וליהוי
פר מן המונח. Veleihavei par min hamunach. Just bring an ox. That's
you know even if you meant a calf, an ox is bigger
than a calf. So the answer here is obvious: הא מני רבי
היא דאמר קטן והביא גדול לא יצא. Ha mani Rebbi hi de'amar
katan vehevi gadol lo yatza. This is going like Rebbi. Rebbi says
that you know if you said small and you bring a big
one you weren't יוצא. yotze. So even if you so if you
said a calf, you wouldn't be יוצא yotze by bringing an ox.
Very reasonable. So the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute. אי רבי
אימא סיפא. Ei Rebbi eima seifa. But wait a minute. Look at
the end. The end assumes that you can make that switch. שור
במנה והביא שניים במנה לא יצא ואפילו זה במנה חסר דינר וזה
במנה חסר דינר. Shor be-maneh vehevi shnayim be-maneh lo yatza ve'afilu zeh
be-maneh chaser dinar ve-zeh be-maneh chaser dinar. So the גמרא's Gemara gonna
be very windy here, okay. So it says if you say an
ox for a hundred you don't fulfill your obligation even if you
bring two of them worth ninety-nine each. שחור והביא לבן, לבן והביא
שחור, גדול והביא קטן לא יצא. Shachor vehevi lavan, lavan vehevi shachor,
gadol vehevi katan lo yatza. Black and white, white black, big if
you say big and you bring small you don't fulfill your obligation.
קטן והביא גדול יצא. Katan vehevi gadol yatza. But it says that
if you say small and you bring big you're יוצא. yotze. And
then we say רבי אומר לא יצא, Rebbi omer lo yatza, you
don't fulfill your obligation. But the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma felt that
small and big works. So why didn't that work when you said
cattle? Just bring the big one. רישא וסיפא רבי מציעתא רבנן? Reisha
veseifa Rebbi metzi'ata Rabbanan? How can you say the first part is
Rebbi that says when you say cattle you have to bring even
a calf, you're not יוצא yotze with a big one, that's Rebbi.
And the end we have Rebbi saying if you say small and
big you're not יוצא. yotze. In the middle we have the rabbis
saying you are יוצא? yotze? Normally since Rebbi isn't until the end
we would assume until Rebbi's position it's all going according to the
חכמים. Chachamim. So the גמרא: Gemara: רישא וסיפא רבי מציעתא רבנן? Reisha
veseifa Rebbi metzi'ata Rabbanan? אין רישא וסיפא רבי מציעתא רבנן. In reisha
veseifa Rebbi metzi'ata Rabbanan. Yes, it is how you read the משנה.
Mishnah. והכי קאמר. Ve-hachi ka'amar. and that is a מחלוקת ר' ורבנן.
machlokes Rebbi v'Rabanan. If it's
first it says when you say cattle you have to bring a
calf and an ox, and that is going according to ר', Rebbi,
you're not יוצא yotzei if you bring an ox. And then it
says, by the way, this issue is really a debate of ר'
Rebbi and the רבנן, Rabanan, because if you say small and bring
big, the רבנן Rabanan actually say you are יוצא, yotzei, but ר'
Rebbi says you're not. And that earlier idea that when you said
cattle you have to bring a calf and an ox and not
just an ox is going according to ר'. Rebbi. Okay, תנן, tnan,
we taught over התם hasam over there in שקלים Shekalim and this
was quoted also a few דפים dappim ago. שישה לנדבה, shisha l'nedava,
there are six horns, there are six boxes, you know where you
put money in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, that the money there
goes for עולות olas to be brought on the מזבח mizbeach when
it's you know when it's not a busy day. Okay, so כנגד
מי, keneged mi, why did you have those six different boxes, why
didn't you just have one box to put all the money in,
and we'll see what type of moneys would be put in there,
things of various קרבנות korbanos that could not be brought for their
original purpose that it would be redeemed and then the money would
be used to bring these עולות olas to keep the מזבח mizbeach
busy. But why did you need six boxes or horns, why not
just you know horn if you think about it like a צדקה
tzedakah box, it's got a narrow opening at the top and it's
wide at the bottom. Okay,
so why did why did you need this, so why did you
need six? So let's take a look. אמר חזקיה amar Chizkiya כנגד
שישה בתי אבות הכהנים שתיקנו להם חכמים שישלום זה עם זה keneged
shisha batei avos ha'kohanim she'tiknu lahem chachamim she'yishalom zeh im zeh
because there were six בתי אבות batei avos of the כוהנים, kohanim,
each there was each משמר mishmar of כוהנים kohanim worked you know
a week in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, they were on a
rotation, 24 of them,
and within each משמר mishmar it was broken up into six families
בתי אבות, batei avos, each family would work a day, Sunday, Monday,
Tuesday, שבת Shabbos they would all work the same. And therefore he
said that this is done so that there would be one שופר
shofar which would be Sunday, one would be Monday, one would be
Tuesday, one would be Wednesday. So if it's your and your day
of the week, your בית אב beis av day of the week,
there's not a lot of animals being brought as קרבנות, korbanos, you
take from your day's שופר shofar and you use it for bringing
these עולות. olas. And that way there's not fighting. Why? Because if
there was only one שופר shofar and you took for your day
on Wednesday there wasn't a lot, then the people and then you
got you know to bring those extra קרבנות korbanot with that communal
money and you got to use the leather and so on, then
the כוהנים kohanim on Thursday and Tuesday would say, hey, you're taking
from those funds and how come you're the only ones benefiting from
them and we're not benefiting from them? Now they could say back,
well, you have a lot of קרבנות korbanot on Tuesday and Thursday,
you didn't need these funds, but nevertheless it would lead to fighting.
So therefore it won't be fighting if each person if each בית
אב beis av is taking from its day and therefore it's not
seen as taking away funds that could be used on the other
day. It's actually interesting that it says כנגד. keneged. כנגד keneged sometimes
means it's symbolically six representing like I don't know you know six
days of the week, six this, like it's just a symbolic number,
but here it actually means that this was the purpose in order
that it would not lead to fighting. ר' יוחנן אומר Rebbi Yochanan
omer מתוך שנדבה מרובה תיקנו להם שופרות מרובות כדי שלא יתעפשו המעות.
mitoch she'nedava meruba tiknu lahem shofaros merubos k'dei she'lo yis'afshu ha'maos. Because
he says no another practical reason that's not specifically had to be
six, but if you had just one שופר shofar people put a
lot of money in it, and especially if it's like copper coins
and it can get rusty and it can get moldy, and therefore
you wanted it spread out in a lot of boxes because it
would be a whole big stuff and it wouldn't get empty for
a while, the stuff would sort of you know get moldy and
or rusty.
וזעירי אמר V'Zeiri amar
כנגד פר ועגל כבש וגדי ושעיר, keneged par v'eigel keves v'gdi v'sa'ir,
exactly, this is probably why we're discussing it right here, all the
different types of animals that could come as an עולה olah or
at least the mammals, right an ox, a calf, a ram, a
sheep, a goat, and a kid goat. ור' היא דאמר קטן בן
גדול לא יצא, V'Rebbi hi d'amar katan ben gadol lo yatza, and
it's going like ר' Rebbi that said that if you say a
big one and you bring a small one you are not יוצא.
yotzei.